Southwest Folklore Archive folk drama collection, 1837-1970
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Southwest Folklore Archive folk drama collection, 1837-1970
SWF 001
Frances Gillmor and Juan B. Rael
1.25 linear feet
This Collection contains Correspondence, Non-Hispanic Folk Dramas, and Mexican and Spanish Folk Dramas that were collected by Frances Gilmor on field trips to Mexico and the southwestern United States..
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Frances Gillmor (1903-1993), was the first Chair of the University of Arizona Folklore Committee, from 1945 to her retirement in 1972, and founded its archives. A novelist and a professor of English at the University of Arizona, she held an M.A. in English from the University (1931). Her studies in Mexican folklore and cultural anthropology subsequently led her to complete a Doctora en Letras at the Universidad Nacional Autònoma de México, awarded in 1957.
Gillmor's diverse interests and research led her around the world. One particular area of interest was the traditional dance dramas of Mexico, a subject upon which she published several studies. In 1959 she received a Guggenheim Fellowship to study folk drama at village fiestas in Spain, for comparison with those of Mexico. Many of the transcripts that she collected have been included in this collection.
Juan B. Rael was a fellow scholar and colleague of Frances Gillmor, who shared her interest in Mexican folk drama. Rael collected material for his book The Sources and Diffusion of the Mexican Shepherds' Plays, published in 1965. These materials are unpublished texts or versions, in manuscript or typescript form, collected on field trips to Mexico and the southwestern United States. The original manuscripts are now housed in the Stanford University Library. These copies were sent unsolicited to Dr. Gillmor in 1967, and were added to the collection.
Organization
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Correspondence, 1966-1970
II. Non-Hispanic Folk Dramas, 1892-1967
III. Mexican and Spanish Folk Dramas, 1837-1967
Scope and Content Note
This collection is divided into three series: Correspondence, Non-Hispanic Folk Dramas, and Mexican and Spanish Folk Dramas, the latter two arranged alphabetically by title. The third series, Mexican and Spanish Folk Dramas, comprises the bulk of the collection, with thirty-eight items. Most of these folk dramas were collected from Mexico, and range in date from 1837 through1961. These are primarily different local versions of Los Pastores or Los Tastoanes collected by Juan B. Rael for his book, The Source and Diffusion of the Mexican Shepherds' Plays. The items are typewritten transcripts of original manuscripts or interviews, with the exception of one holographic manuscript donated to Dr. Gillmor by Carmen Celia Beltrán, Sarzuela Pastoril Para la Noche-Buena, from 1902.
Most materials are in Spanish.
Related Materials
Other materials regarding folk dramas are located in the Papers of Frances Gillmor (MS 333).
Access Terms
Pastoral drama, Mexican; Pastoral drama, Spanish -- Mexico; Christmas plays, Spanish -- Mexico; Folk drama, Spanish -- Mexico
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1966-1970
  Letters between Dr. Frances Gillmor and Dr. Juan Rael and Carmen Celia Beltrán regarding the donation of folk dramas to the archive. Copies of letters between Gillmor and informants regarding their information. Letters regarding individual folk drama acquisitions also appear in the related item folders in this collection.
  - Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Non-Hispanic Folk Dramas, 1892-1967
  Reports and papers on plays and stories from Newfoundland, Ireland, and Innsbruck, Austria.
  - Donaldson, Myrtle N., "The Easter Plays of Muxi and Innsbruck, Austria." (student paper). 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newfoundland Play by Mummer Productions. 1892 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Story from Ireland. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III: Mexican and Spanish Folk Dramas, 1837-1967
  The bulk of this series consists of typewritten transcripts of folk dramas copied from the original documents or obtained through interviews with participants. Also included are transcripts of interviews and one photocopy of a damaged holographic manuscript housed at the University of New Mexico library. There is also one fragile handwritten manuscript entitled Sarzuela Pastoril Para la Noche-Buena (1902). Users are restricted to a working photocopy of this play.
  - Interview transcription: Christmas Traditions. Miniatitlan, Veracruz, Mexico. 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - La aquila negra. Ensayo, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Colocio [sic] de dansa [sic] de conquista. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Coloquio de la danza de conquista. Lomas de Paradero, Guadalajara, Mexico. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Coloquio de San Jose y de Maria. Fresnillo, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cuaderno del coloquio de pastores Dedicado al Nacimiento de Nuestro Sr. Jesucristo. New Mexico. Copy of manuscript housed at the Unviersity of New Mexico Library. No Date (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cuaderno de pastorela. Monterrey, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cuaderno de pastorela para Uso de la Señora Maria Antuna. Durango, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cuaderno de pastores. Saltillo, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Los cuatro apariciones de la Virgin de Guadalupe. Hermosillo, Sonora, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Entrada de moros y cristianos. Cuenca, España. No Date (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Entrada de moros y cristianos. Poveda de la Sierra, España. 1889 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Juan Diego and the Virgin of Guadalupe. Zapopan, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - El Paracutin. Calzontzin, Michoacan, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Paso de los Santos Reyes. Matape, Sonora, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Los pastores. Cajititlan, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Los pastores. Cuba, New Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Los pastores. Tonala, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Los pastores. La adoracion de los pastores. Tepupa, Sonora, Mexico. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pastorela de los siete vicios o sea el nacimiento de niño Dios. Aguascalientes, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Pastorela. Guadalupe, Zacatecas, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pastorela. Coronel Collection, Los Angeles County Museum. 1839 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pastorela: Navidad entre pastores. Guadalajara, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pastorela titulada "Los siete principes". Guadalupe, Zacatecas, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Las posadas. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Los Santos Reyes. Cajititlan, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sarzeula pastoril para la noche-buena. 1902 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sueño de Luzbel. Coronel Collection, Los Angeles County Museum. 1837 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Sueño de Luzbel. Coronel Collection, Los Angeles County Museum. 1861 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Los tastoanes. Guadalajara, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Los tastoanes. Guadalajara, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Los tastoanes. Jocotan, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Los tastoanes. Jocotan, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Los tastoanes. Nextipac, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Los tastoanes. Salatitan, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Los tastoanes. San Juan, Ocotan, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Los tastoanes. Tonala, Jalisco, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Tehualiles. Sahuayo, Michoacan, Mexico. No Date (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Sarzeula pastoril para la noche-buena. Restricted original manuscript, use photocopy located in folder 31. 1902 (Box 1, Folder 43)